Chapter 59. squid.
Slowly waiting through the meadows of Brit, the Peekquad still held on her way
northeastward towards the island of Java, a gentle air impelling her keel,
so that in the surrounding serenity, her three tall tapering masss mildly waved
to that languid breeze as three mild palms on a plane. And still at wide
intervals in the silvery night the lonely alluring jet would be seen.
But one transparent blue morning when a stillness almost preternatural spread
over the sea, however unattended with any stagnant calm, when the long
burnished sunlade on the waters seemed a golden finger laid across them enjoining
some secrecy. When these slippered waves whispered together as they softly ran
on, in this profound hush of the visible sphere, a strange spectre was seen by
Dagu from the main mast head. In the distance a great white mass lazily rose
and rising higher and higher and disentangling itself from the azure at
last gleamed before our prow like a snows slide new slid from the hills.
Thus glistening for a moment as slowly it subsided and sank. Then once more
arose and silently gleamed. It seemed not a whale. And yet is this Moby Dick?
thought Deu again. The phantom went down, but on reappearing once more with a
stiletto-like cry that startled every man from his nod, the negro yelled out,
"There, there again. There she breaches.
Right ahead. The white whale. The white whale."
Upon this the seaman rushed to the yard arms, as in swarming times the bees
rushed to the boughs. Bareheaded in the sultry sun, Ahab stood on the bowsprit,
and with one hand pushed far behind in readiness to wave his orders to the
helmsmen, cast his eager glance in the direction indicated a loft by the
outstretched motionless arm of Dagu.
whether the flitting attendance of one still and solitary jet had gradually
worked upon Ahab, so that he was now prepared to connect the ideas of
mildness and repose, with the first sight of the particular whale he
pursued, however this was, or whether his eagerness betrayed him, whichever
way it might have been, no sooner did he distinctly perceive the white mass, then
with a quick intensity he instantly gave orders for lowering. ing. The four boats
were soon on the water, Ahabs in advance, and all swiftly pulling towards
their prey. Soon it went down, and while, with ores suspended, we were
awaiting its reappearance, low, in the same spot where it sank. Once more it
slowly rose, almost forgetting for a moment all thoughts of Moby Dick, we
gazed at the most wondrous phenomenon which the secret seas have hitherto
revealed to mankind. A vast pulpy mass furlongs in length and breadth of a
glancing cream color lay floating on the water, innumerable long arms radiating
from its center, and curling and twisting like a nest of anacondas, as if
blindly to clutch at any hapless object within reach. No perceptible face or
front did it have no conceivable token of either sensation or instinct, but
undulated there on the billows, an unearly, formless, chancelike apparition of life.
As with a low sucking sound, it slowly disappeared again. Starbucks, still
gazing at the agitated waters where it had sunk, with a wild voice, exclaimed.
Almost rather had I seen Moby Dick and fought him, than to have seen thee, thou white ghost.
What was it, sir, said Flask? the great live squid, which they say few whale
ships ever beheld, and returned to their ports to Telvet.
But Ahab said nothing. Turning his boat, he sailed back to the vessel, the rest
as silently following.
Whatever superstitions the sperm whalemen in general have connected with
the sight of this object, certain it is that a glimpse of it being so very
unusual, that circumstance has gone far to invest it with portentiousness, so
rarely is it beheld that though one and all of them declare it to be the largest
animated thing in the ocean, yet very few of them have any but the most vague
ideas concerning its true nature and form. Notwithstanding, they believe it
to furnish the sperm whale his only food. For though other species of whales
find their food above water, and may be seen by man in the act of feeding, the
spermiceti whale obtains his whole food in unknown zones below the surface. And
only by inference is it that anyone can tell of what precisely that food
consists. At times when closely pursued, he will disgorge what are supposed to be
the detached arms of the squid. Some of them thus exhibited exceeding 20 and 30
ft in length. They fancy that the monster to which these arms belonged
ordinarily clings by them to the bed of the oceans, and that the sperm whale,
unlike other species, is supplied with teeth in order to attack and tear it.
There seems some ground to imagine that the great kraken of Bishop Pontapadan
may ultimately resolve itself into squid. The manner in which the bishop
describes it as alternately rising and sinking with some other particulars he
narrates. In all this the two correspond but much abatement is necessary with
respect to the incredible bulk he assigns it. by some naturalists who have
vaguely heard rumors of the mysterious creature here spoken of. It is included
among the class of cuttlefish to which indeed in certain external respects it
would seem to belong, but only as the anac of the tribe.